ALI LARA

alilarag@mail.com • (614) 440-6494 • aliglara @ Linkedin • Austin, TX

SUMMARY

Analytical mindset, having extensive experience extracting useful facts from data. Enjoy open-ended issues and the application of developing technologies to challenging cases in various sectors. Good communicator with an optimistic outlook and a desire to solve problems.

EXPERIENCE

Process Assistant, Amazon, Austin, TX

Mar 2023 - present

- Supervised a 35-member team aimed at developing an effective inbound workflow for processing 70k+ packages daily
- Streamlined the implemented workflow to reduce setup and processing time in a safe environment
- Assessed and developed production and labor plans
- Adapted team resources based on statistical real-time manufacturing metrics
- Collaborated with leadership team in performing continuous evaluation of work methods, procedures, and policies
- Tracked performance and supports any identified retraining opportunities for T1-associates

Yard Marshal, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Dec 2021 - Mar 2023

- Coordinated with carriers to ensure timely and accurate delivery of goods to customers
- Handled dispatching duties and managed shipment tracking
- Maintained digital records of 20+ inbound and outbound linehauls on a daily basis
- Assisted in carrier contract negotiations and compliance
- Monitored Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) and reported results to management
- Authored an Excel-based tracking tool to reduce process defects in 75%
- Partnered a 15-member team aimed at developing efficient loading/unloading system for 40k+ of packages daily
- Monitored adherence to the established training programs to ensure standard work under a safe environment

FC Associate, Amazon, Columbus, OH

Nov 2020 - Dec 2021

- Seeked ongoing skill development on under-performing associates to meet production goals
- Outperformed KPIs designed for tracking T1-associates performance: 379 UPH, 500+ average stow rate which represented being at the 95th percentile
- Classified hazardous residues following federal and local EPA/RCRA standards for handling, disposal or shipping
- Used technical knowledge to troubleshoot any issues related to damaged packages, processing hazmats, returns, and third-party contractor shipping
- Assisted to learning coordinator for coaching Day-1 and Week-1 associates in standards of work, and safety culture

Machine Learning Engineer II, MCL Control, Venezuela

May 2012 - Sep 2019

- Served as Team Leader from design to execution of machine learning algorithms to develop predictive models and optimize the performance of advanced control process algorithms for rotary industrial machinery
- Managed data-driven solutions team of three researchers, identified vulnerabilities, tested solutions, established standardized workflow, and executed programs in oil/gas industry
- Constructed neural network models in Python/Tensorflow to estimate theorical physical parameters required by process simulations built on Aspen Hysys to improve the application performance
- Managed a 10-junior engineers' team over a one-year period and coached them on using XGBoost and random forest models to optimize the feature selection, via ROC/AUC metrics, for proposed machine learning solutions
- Executed more than five process simulation models per year, performing optimization studies, and preparing technical papers and presentations
- Gathered information, identified analytical requirements, and developed data-driven based models to translate complex business needs into actionable analytic projects
- Developed an assistive tool to perform HAZOP studies based on autoregressive models and machine learning techniques in compliance with design specifications
- Designed and implemented machine learning models to detect problems and predict failures using deep learning techniques, primarily for turbo-compressors and turbofans

- Researched chemical reaction engineering, mathematical modeling, simulation and optimization, process synthesis
 and design including economic assessments, process integration, and machine learning techniques for industrial
 process evaluation
- Lectured in several chemical engineering areas including thermodynamics, chemical reactor design, numerical methods, industrial process simulation, and statistical modeling
- Implemented a problem-solved learning experience in different subjects following the ABET guidance.
- Coached 200+ chemical engineering undergraduates with regards to academic pathways and toward degree completion and established and provided career counseling for a network of cooperatives, internships, and externships to foster academic to industry pipeline
- Mentored students throughout the process, developed semesterly goals and advised on study abroad opportunities based on the double-degree program of the Politecnico di Torino, and Sapienza University of Rome (Italy), IFP School (France), IESA School of Management (Venezuela), and Florida International University (USA)

PROJECTS

Miss Direction Aug 2016

A mapping engine that misguides you:

- Won award at AIHacks 2016
- Built by all women team of newbie programmers
- Using modern technologies such as GoogleMaps, Chrome Extension and Javascript

EDUCATION

DataCamp.com, Python for Data Scientist

2017

Universidad Central of Venezuela, M.Sc. Chemical Engineering

2005 - 2008

Universidad Central of Venezuela, B.Sc. Chemical Engineering

1990 - 1998

SKILLS

- Process modeling: Statistical modeling, Matlab, Hysys
- Data Analysis: Excel, SQL, noSQL, Tableau
- Machine learning: Python, R, Tensorflow